<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://flyinghopmachine.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-16T19:22:45-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What in The World is That Off-flavor?]]></title>
    <link href="http://flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/14/what-in-the-world-is-that-off-flavor/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/14/what-in-the-world-is-that-off-flavor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a couple of years brewing I came across one of the biggest difficulties
in my brewing to date. A bold, in your face, undeniable off-flavor had plagued
my (home) brewhouse. The flavor was medicinal, plastic-like, pool-like and very
very overruling. I lost three 5 gallon batches of homebrew, and this is the
story of my quest to find out what was the cause.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I had never had a such a <em>bad</em> batch before then, and by bad I mean bad
process, not bad recipe. I screwed up many a recipes before. The intensity in
this flavor got me chasing a ghost for a few months. During these period, I
brewed these beers:</p>

<ol>
<li>Saison</li>
<li>Rye Smoked Porter</li>
<li>Rye IPA</li>
<li>Rye Smoked Porter (again)</li>
</ol>


<p>In terms of brewing process, I made a few changes before this off-flavor
appeared in my beers: Use a yeast starter, wort aeration with an aquarium pump
and diffusion stone, and using yeast nutrients. These changes were correcting
high-gravity beers which were coming out under-attenuated.</p>

<p>I first noticed the flavor on the Saison and the Smoked Porter, both of which I
brewed close enough to each other that I didn&rsquo;t know they both had this
issue as they were fermenting.</p>

<p>I brewed the Rye IPA pretty much the day I found out about the off-flavor as
I racked them to kegs, and so I didn&rsquo;t really change anything about my
equipment or process for that brew. I was pretty much sending a batch of wort
to ferment, not knowing if it would have this flavor too. I went on
regardless.</p>

<h2>The quest begins</h2>

<p>First off, for the Rye IPA batch, I sampled it at various points during the
brewing process and fermentation to try and determine where it was coming from.</p>

<p>Then I took the Saison and the Smoked Porter to my awesome LHBS. After tasting
it there I was convinced this was not an easy thing to fix. The advice I got
was to deep clean everything, and to replace racking canes or hoses that might
be suspect.</p>

<p>I chill my wort with a <a href="http://www.blichmannengineering.com/products/therminator">plate
chiller</a>, so the
output wort hose for this was suspect, as well as the chiller itself. I later
replaced this hose, as well as my racking cane which had some buildup. It turns
out you can&rsquo;t <em>really</em> clean racking canes well, it&rsquo;s good to replace these
every 6 - 12 months or so depending on how much you brew. I also got a hose
cleaning brush as I noticed some buildup in some hoses as well as in the
in-line <a href="http://www.blichmannengineering.com/products/thrumometer">ThruMometer</a></p>

<p>I also took the Saison and the Smoked Porter to my homebrew meetup, which
includes many experienced brewers as well as a BJCP judge. The obvious flavor
was there, everyone agreed, but nobody could tell me definitively where the
flavor came from. I got conflicting advice in that some folks assured me it
wasn&rsquo;t a bacterial or infection induced flavor as those tend to turn beer
acidic. So indeed, the plot thickens.</p>

<p>Next up, I kegged my Rye IPA, and I was surprised and relieved that it didn&rsquo;t
also have the off-flavor. This was one of those beers that went fast because it
was so darn delicious!</p>

<p>Confident in the fact that there was nothing wrong with my equipment at this
point, I went on to brew my Rye Smoked Porter again. At this point, I had
deep-cleaned all of my equipment, replaced suspect parts, and knew that it was
clean of any bacteria. After all, the previous brew went just fine.</p>

<p>This time around, I tried my wort/beer every step of the way, too. No signs of
this flavor on brewday, so pitched my starter yeast, and off to primary
fermentation it goes.</p>

<p>I sampled the fermenting beer 3 days in and it was clean. Five days in, same
thing. I&rsquo;m safe, I thought. Let it ferment all the way, for about 14 days, and
to my surprise the flavor was back when I kegged.</p>

<p>I still carbonated it. Before I poured this batch down the drain, I saved a few
bottles to get more help identifying what&rsquo;s up. I gave a bottle to a local
friendly brewery, <a href="http://www.cleoph.us/">Cleophus Quealy</a>, who also asked me
for the recipe and brewing notes.</p>

<p>Brewing notes included the usual brewday notes, but most notably that I used my
local tap water, but removed chlorine with campden tablets and boiling
treatment, something that I&rsquo;ve done successfuly in brews past.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what they had to say:</p>

<blockquote><p>Strong antiseptic flavor. The phenols in the smoke are mixing crazy with possibly the chlorine in the water.  I would ditch the campden tables and go to carbon filtering. Pretty hard to diagnose with that strong off flavor. Biggest guess is chlorophenols esp with the smoked malts.</p></blockquote>


<h2>ChloroWHAT?</h2>

<p>Yeah, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chlorophenol">chlorophenols</a>. These nasty
compounds are formed when phenols bond with chlorine. Phenol production is
evident in some malts and yeasts, notably smoked malts and some yeasts such as
the <a href="https://www.wyeastlab.com/rw_yeaststrain_detail.cfm?ID=199among">WY3711</a>
used here among many others, but not really on
<a href="http://www.whitelabs.com/yeast/wlp001-california-ale-yeast">WLP001</a> used for
the Rye IPA.</p>

<p>Alright, so this makes sense, but does this mean that campden tablets don&rsquo;t
work? No, it doesn&rsquo;t, and here&rsquo;s the last piece of the puzzle: I started
getting these off-flavors when I changed something about my brewing process,
and the key in the yeast starter. I was just using tap water with no filtration
or treatment to build my starters. Even though we&rsquo;re just talking less than a
couple of liters of water, this seams to fit the bill.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve since switched to using RO or carbon-filtered water for my starters, and
haven&rsquo;t had a problem again, even after brewing the same recipes pressumably
containing the same phenol production.</p>

<h2>Lessons and Conclusions</h2>

<ul>
<li>Do not mess with Chlorine. I still trust campden tablets, but carbon
filtration, reverse osmosis, distillation, and boiling treatments are also
effective.</li>
<li>Beware of your yeast starter water! It can ruin a batch or three.</li>
<li>Good cleaning and sanitation practices are crucial. I always thought I did a
good job at this, but in the face of this issue I wasn&rsquo;t <em>sure</em> - there was
always a chance I was messing something up. As a result, I am now even more
thorough about cleaning and sanitation, and going forward an off-flavor will
be less likely to be sanitation related and might lead me to finding the
cause faster.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
