<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sour | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/sour/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-09T12:37:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Salty Dog Gose]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/08/03/brew-day-salty-dog-gose/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-03T20:57:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/08/03/brew-day-salty-dog-gose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been itching to bring in some critters into my brewery that weren&rsquo;t
saccharomyces for a little while. I&rsquo;ve been making a bit of research and
finally decided to jump right in. I think a Gose (or a Berliner Weisse for that
matter) are a great way to start this journey, because it does not require long
aging periods, and with hot side souring, it can reduce the chance of infecting
brewery equipment with bacteria.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>For this beer, I did what&rsquo;s called Kettle Souring or Sour Wort (?). The process
is fairly straightforward. It involves mashing as you usually would, chilling
wort to a range appropriate for your lactobacillus cultures, pitching
lactobacillus, and holding the temperature for a few days. Then, you may or may
not boil this wort, chill again as usual and pitch saccharomyces.</p>

<p>Lactobacillus eats up sugars and produce lactic acid which in turn lowers the
solution&rsquo;s pH. When souring wort, having a pH meter is important as it will
tell you when to stop. If it drops too low, then saccharomyces will be
inhibited, and if it&rsquo;s too high, then it won&rsquo;t be sour. Tasting the wort as you
measure pH is good advice as well - you&rsquo;ll know how it&rsquo;s progressing and when
it&rsquo;s just too much, although when it&rsquo;s carbonated it will be perceived as less
sour.</p>

<p>A characteristic of Goses is that they do not have any IBUs. I didn&rsquo;t add any
hops at all, except for a few in the mash just for fun. But it&rsquo;s notable that
in general hops will inhibit lactobacillus activity, again, depending on
species, so generally these beers have very little hops if at all.</p>

<p>For this time around, I am trying to go as simple as possible to get a feel for
the process. I did some research on the style, and ended up with the following
recipe:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th>  IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td>  0     </td>
<td> 1.048 </td>
<td> ?     </td>
<td> ?   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Water</em></p>

<p>Water chemistry was not something I found a lot of good information about.
Because this is a very light-colored beer, I started off with RO water. But I
didn&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;d be wise to go with completely soft water either, and it&rsquo;s not
a hoppy beer so I don&rsquo;t need a high sulfate to chloride ratio.  I just added a
quarter tsp of both Calcium Chloride and Gypsum in my strike water.  Along with
a little bit of acidulated malt that I included in the grist, this should bring
my mash pH to appropriate conversion levels.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, my pH meter broke down on brew day, so I was unable to measure
mash pH, nor wort starting pH prior to pitching lactobacillus. I&rsquo;ll just have
to measure these on my next Gose.</p>

<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                    </th>
<th> Amount    </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Weyermann Wheat Malt    </td>
<td> 5 lb      </td>
<td> 47.6 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Weyermann Pilsener Malt </td>
<td> 4 lb 8 oz </td>
<td> 42.9 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Melanoidin Malt         </td>
<td> 4 oz      </td>
<td> 2.4 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acidulated Malt         </td>
<td> 4 oz      </td>
<td> 2.4 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rice Hulls              </td>
<td> 8 oz      </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Hop Schedule</em></p>

<p>Three fresh chinook hops from your garden in the mash (optional) :)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20163262111/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/492/20163262111_daba90c00b_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Other</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount       </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet     </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yeast Nutrient                                   </td>
<td> &frac14; teaspoon </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Crushed Coriander                                </td>
<td> 1 oz         </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Maldon Sea Salt Flakes                           </td>
<td> 14 grams     </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20200975175/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/451/20200975175_9d6b52857e_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Yeast</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                     </th>
<th> Lab         </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
<th> Amount                      </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> GB110 Fast Souring Lacto </td>
<td> GigaYeast   </td>
<td> 15%         </td>
<td> 1 bag in 2 liter starter    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> WLP029 German Ale/Kölsch </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 78%         </td>
<td> 1 vial in 1.8 liter starter </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>July 26, 2015</h4>

<p>Built a starter inoculate with the lactobacillus package. I made it 2 full
liters. Chilled it to 95F. After pitching the package, the Erlenmeyer flask
filled pretty much to the top, which was the goal as to avoid any oxygen
between the wort and the bung. Placed an airlock and sealed it by wrapping
around with cling wrap.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/19969590068/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/383/19969590068_2a0f76a697_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h4>July 30, 2015</h4>

<p>Mashed in at 148F. Added calcium chloride and gypsum additions. Sparged and
boiled for 15 minutes to help volatalize DMS from the pilsener malt.</p>

<p>During the boil, I quickly cleaned up my plastic cooler/mash tun to be used
during wort souring to aid in maintaining an appropriate temperature.</p>

<p>Chilled wort using plate chiller straight into cooler, targeting 99-100F. It
wasn&rsquo;t easy to get this temperature, but by controlling the flow of water it
got it down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20014356589/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/281/20014356589_b37e6beb75_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>SG reading was 1.048.</p>

<p>Pitched entire lactobacillus starter into wort. After pitching, temperature was
98F.</p>

<p>Purged oxygen with CO2, closed down the cooler, and placed in warmest place
possible. Ideally you&rsquo;d control temperature and maintain it at 98F, which I
don&rsquo;t have equipment to do yet.</p>

<h4>July 30, 2015</h4>

<p>20 hours later, pH dropped to 3.5 and temperature dropped to 87F. I know it&rsquo;s
called &ldquo;Fast Souring Lacto&rdquo; but this seems <em>very</em> fast! Probably also due to
the fact that RO water was used, and I didn&rsquo;t add any bicarbonates, so
alkalinity on this water is definitely low.</p>

<p>Built a started with one vial of WLP029 and yeast nutrients.</p>

<h4>Aug 1, 2015</h4>

<p>pH dropped to 3.3 and temperature to 80F. It&rsquo;s definitely time to stop
lactobacillus activity, which I did by boiling the wort.</p>

<p>Wort tasted nice and sour, but very clean. Getting pumped!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20183503406/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5617/20183503406_8bfd689c58_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I crushed the coriander seeds by placing them in a bag and using a kitchen
roller.</p>

<p>During the boil I added a Whirfloc tablet, yeast nutrients, coriander and salt</p>

<p>After boiling it, chilled as usual, aerated, and pitched WLP029 starter.</p>

<p>SG reading was 1.023, so this lacto did attenuate the wort a bit.</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;d do differently</h2>

<ul>
<li>For the lactobacillus starter, there are
<a href="http://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Lactobacillus#Starters_and_Pitching_Rate">experiments</a>
which show using a bit of apple juice yield a more appropriate environment for
lacto. Further, I&rsquo;ll add some yeast nutrients which I didn&rsquo;t do this time.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;d do more research on appropriate water profile, although it seems to me
chloride and sulfate won&rsquo;t play a big role in a sour beer like this. I might
consider simply using acidulated malt and phophoric acid to tune in on an
appropriate mash pH.</li>
<li>I boiled for a full 60 minutes, but I don&rsquo;t see any reason to having done
that. Next time, a 15 minute wort with the remaining ingredients might be
enough.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll add &ldquo;test pH meter&rdquo; to my pre-brewing flight check.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>This is all new to me: how else can I improve this process? Please let me know
in the comments!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
