<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: brewday | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/brewday/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-03T21:59:21-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Salty Dog Gose]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/08/03/brew-day-salty-dog-gose/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-03T20:57:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/08/03/brew-day-salty-dog-gose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been itching to bring in some critters into my brewery that weren&rsquo;t
saccharomyces for a little while. I&rsquo;ve been making a bit of research and
finally decided to jump right in. I think a Gose (or a Berliner Weisse for that
matter) are a great way to start this journey, because it does not require long
aging periods, and with hot side souring, it can reduce the chance of infecting
brewery equipment with bacteria.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>For this beer, I did what&rsquo;s called Kettle Souring or Sour Wort (?). The process
is fairly straightforward. It involves mashing as you usually would, chilling
wort to a range appropriate for your lactobacillus cultures, pitching
lactobacillus, and holding the temperature for a few days. Then, you may or may
not boil this wort, chill again as usual and pitch saccharomyces.</p>

<p>Lactobacillus eats up sugars and produce lactic acid which in turn lowers the
solution&rsquo;s pH. When souring wort, having a pH meter is important as it will
tell you when to stop. If it drops too low, then saccharomyces will be
inhibited, and if it&rsquo;s too high, then it won&rsquo;t be sour. Tasting the wort as you
measure pH is good advice as well - you&rsquo;ll know how it&rsquo;s progressing and when
it&rsquo;s just too much, although when it&rsquo;s carbonated it will be perceived as less
sour.</p>

<p>A characteristic of Goses is that they do not have any IBUs. I didn&rsquo;t add any
hops at all, except for a few in the mash just for fun. But it&rsquo;s notable that
in general hops will inhibit lactobacillus activity, again, depending on
species, so generally these beers have very little hops if at all.</p>

<p>For this time around, I am trying to go as simple as possible to get a feel for
the process. I did some research on the style, and ended up with the following
recipe:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th>  IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td>  0     </td>
<td> 1.030 </td>
<td> ?     </td>
<td> ?   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Water</em></p>

<p>Water chemistry was not something I found a lot of good information about.
Because this is a very light-colored beer, I started off with RO water. But I
didn&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;d be wise to go with completely soft water either, and it&rsquo;s not
a hoppy beer so I don&rsquo;t need a high sulfate to chloride ratio.  I just added a
quarter tsp of both Calcium Chloride and Gypsum in my strike water.  Along with
a little bit of acidulated malt that I included in the grist, this should bring
my mash pH to appropriate conversion levels.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, my pH meter broke down on brew day, so I was unable to measure
mash pH, nor wort starting pH prior to pitching lactobacillus. I&rsquo;ll just have
to measure these on my next Gose.</p>

<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                    </th>
<th> Amount    </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Weyermann Wheat Malt    </td>
<td> 5 lb      </td>
<td> 47.6 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Weyermann Pilsener Malt </td>
<td> 5 lb 8 oz </td>
<td> 42.9 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Melanoidin Malt         </td>
<td> 4 oz      </td>
<td> 2.4 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acidulated Malt         </td>
<td> 4 oz      </td>
<td> 2.4 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rice Hulls              </td>
<td> 8 oz      </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Hop Schedule</em></p>

<p>Three fresh chinook hops from your garden in the mash (optional) :)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20163262111/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/492/20163262111_daba90c00b_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Other</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount       </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet     </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yeast Nutrient                                   </td>
<td> &frac14; teaspoon </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Crushed Coriander                                </td>
<td> 1 oz         </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Maldon Sea Salt Flakes                           </td>
<td> 14 grams     </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20200975175/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/451/20200975175_9d6b52857e_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Yeast</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                     </th>
<th> Lab         </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
<th> Amount                      </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> GB110 Fast Souring Lacto </td>
<td> GigaYeast   </td>
<td> 15%         </td>
<td> 1 bag in 2 liter starter    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> WLP029 German Ale/Kölsch </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 78%         </td>
<td> 1 vial in 1.8 liter starter </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>July 26, 2015</h4>

<p>Built a starter inoculate with the lactobacillus package. I made it 2 full
liters. After pitching the package, the Erlenmeyer flask filled pretty much to
the top, which was the goal as to avoid any oxygen between the wort and the
bung. Placed an airlock and sealed it by wrapping around with cling wrap.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/19969590068/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/383/19969590068_2a0f76a697_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h4>July 30, 2015</h4>

<p>Mashed in at 148F. Added calcium chloride and gypsum additions. Sparged and
boiled for 15 minutes to help volatalize DMS from the pilsener malt.</p>

<p>During the boil, I quickly cleaned up my plastic cooler/mash tun to be used
during wort souring to aid in maintaining an appropriate temperature.</p>

<p>Chilled wort using plate chiller straight into cooler, targeting 99-100F. It
wasn&rsquo;t easy to get this temperature, but by controlling the flow of water it
got it down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20014356589/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/281/20014356589_b37e6beb75_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>SG reading was 1.035.</p>

<p>Pitched entire lactobacillus starter into wort. After pitching, temperature was
98F.</p>

<p>Purged oxygen with CO2, closed down the cooler, and placed in warmest place
possible. Ideally you&rsquo;d control temperature and maintain it at 98F, which I
don&rsquo;t have equipment to do yet.</p>

<h4>July 30, 2015</h4>

<p>20 hours later, pH dropped to 3.5 and temperature dropped to 87F.</p>

<p>Built a started with one vial of WLP029 and yeast nutrients.</p>

<h4>Aug 1, 2015</h4>

<p>pH dropped to 3.3 and temperature to 80F. It&rsquo;s definitely time to stop
lactobacillus activity, which I did by boiling the wort.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20183503406/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5617/20183503406_8bfd689c58_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I crushed the coriander seeds by placing them in a bag and using a kitchen
roller.</p>

<p>During the boil I added a Whirfloc tablet, yeast nutrients, coriander and salt</p>

<p>After boiling it, chilled as usual, aerated, and pitched WLP029 starter.</p>

<p>SG reading was 1.023, so this lacto did attenuate the wort a bit.</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;d do differently</h2>

<ul>
<li>For the lactobacillus starter, there are experiments which show using a bit of
apple juice yield a more appropriate environment for lacto. Further, I&rsquo;ll add
some yeast nutrients which I didn&rsquo;t do this time.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;d do more research on appropriate water profile, although it seems to me
chloride and sulfate won&rsquo;t play a big role in a sour beer like this. I might
consider simply using acidulated malt and phophoric acid to tune in on an
appropriate mash pH.</li>
<li>I boiled for a full 60 minutes, but I don&rsquo;t see any reason to having done
that. Next time, a 15 minute wort with the remaining ingredients might be
enough.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll add &ldquo;test pH meter&rdquo; to my pre-brewing flight check.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Bourbon Barrel Imperial Stout]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/25/brew-day-bourbon-barrel-imperial-stout/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T22:12:03-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/25/brew-day-bourbon-barrel-imperial-stout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started thinking about the holidays at year-end and wanted to brew something
that is a bit heavier and delicious for the colder weather. I decided to go
with an imperial stout. A beer like this needs to be let to sit for a few
months to let it peak, which means it&rsquo;s time to brew it now. I plan on transfering
this beer to secondary or a keg in about three weeks and let it mature there until
late November.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Providing a nice Bourbon Barrel character is easy at a homebrew scale. Just
soak some oak cubes in your favorite burbon for a few days, the oaks absorb the
liquor like sponges.  Then place them in a hop bag and add them to the beer.
This has worked for me before, but there&rsquo;s no reason adding plain oaks to the
beer and blending the spirit directly wouldn&rsquo;t work as well. Soaking them in
bourbon first is convenient however, as it helps sanitize the oak cubes and so
it&rsquo;s not necessary to boil them before use.</p>

<p>For this beer I&rsquo;m looking for something bold, with lots of the characteristic
stout roasted malt character, smokey and coffee notes, not too sweet, full
bodied and lots of alcohol. I wanted the base malt to have some character to
it, and considered Maris Otter or other british malts. I also wanted to include
some rye to go with the bourbon theme, so ended up adding some flaked rye, which
should also aid with head stabilization.</p>

<p>The recipe is the following:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th> Boil Time </th>
<th> IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td> 60m       </td>
<td> 47    </td>
<td> 1.085 </td>
<td> ?     </td>
<td> ?   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/19995083432/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/19995083432_7c89e32491_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Water</em></p>

<p>For this beer, I simply used tap water from my area which has a very high
alkalinity as calcium carbonate and usually plays well with dark beers. The
only water adjustments done were a campden tablet to remove chlorine, and
&frac12; a teaspoon of Calcium Chloride in the boil kettle, enough to have a higher
chloride to sulfate ratio.</p>

<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                  </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Crisp Best Ale Malt   </td>
<td> 16.5 lb </td>
<td> 78.6 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Roasted Barley        </td>
<td> 1 lb    </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Chocolate Malt        </td>
<td> 1 lb    </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> CaraMunich            </td>
<td> 1 lb    </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black Patent Malt     </td>
<td> 8 oz    </td>
<td> 2.4 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Rye            </td>
<td> 1 lb    </td>
<td> 4.8 %       </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Hop Schedule</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Variety            </th>
<th> Time   </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Form       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Challenger         </td>
<td> 60m    </td>
<td> 2 oz   </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fuggle             </td>
<td> 10m    </td>
<td> 1 oz   </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> East Kent Goldings </td>
<td> 1m     </td>
<td> 1 oz   </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Other</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount       </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet     </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yeast Nutrient                                   </td>
<td> &frac14; teaspoon </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Yeast</em></p>

<p>Create a big starter with lots of yeast!</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                   </th>
<th> Lab         </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> WLP007 Dry English Ale </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 70 - 80%    </td>
<td> 2 vials </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> WLP002 English Ale     </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 63 - 70%    </td>
<td> 1 vial  </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/19989401981/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/294/19989401981_4f8febf939_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>July 25, 2015</h4>

<p>I collected 11 gallons of tap water, crushed a campden tablet and added it to the water. Ensured it dissolved completely. I transfered 6 and &frac14; gallons to my HLT and heated it up to 165F. Doughed in and mash started with a temperature of 151F.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgmnz/20002837585/in/album-72157655784368350/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3676/20002837585_566b7ec8b5_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Slowly sparged with the rest of the water. Sparge took a full hour.</p>

<p>Added &frac12; teaspoon of Calcium Chloride to wort in kettle and turned on the burner.</p>

<p>Waited 10 minutes for hot break, and started the 60m countdown. Followed hop and other kettle additions.</p>

<p>Once the hour was complete, chilled wort to 70F and started aerating. Aerated for 45m, and pitched starter. Stirrer bar dropped into beer, woops!</p>

<p>Measured OG was 1.085.</p>

<p>Pitched the starter. Set up a blowoff tube right away, I expect aggressive fermentation.</p>

<p>This fermentation started <em>fast</em>. It had a lag time of just three hours.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Independence Saison]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T20:36:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I brewed a variation on a recipe that I&rsquo;ve worked on for some time. This
beer is being brewed for a special professional event. I&rsquo;ll be given the chance
to talk about the brewing process, and given the audience is engineers and
bio-medical scientists I might dive into water chemistry and focus on that.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I was asked to bring what I consider to be &ldquo;my best brew.&rdquo; This is of course a
terrible question to ask a brewer, just like a dad doesn&rsquo;t have a favorite
child. Right, right? So instead I thought about who the audience is, what the
environment is like, and what I thought they&rsquo;d like the most. There will be
other homebrewers and there will be a prize for best beer, so let&rsquo;s aim for
that! In this case, I think I&rsquo;ll be pouring beer to engineers who are open to
some experimentation but aren&rsquo;t really familiar with the breadth of flavors that
exist in beer, so I wanted to step a bit outside their comfort area while still
bringing something approachable and very drinkable for many palettes. I had to
stay away from harsh or aggressive flavors, but want it to be exotic enough to
leave an impression. Things like barley wine, double/tripple IPAs, Imperial
stouts, might be a bit too aggressive for this purpose. On the other hand Pale
Ales, Pilseners, or Kölsh might be too safe. I decided to go with a saison that
has enough of an edge to be interesting, but might be familiar in other ways
such as color and hop profile. We&rsquo;ll see how this goes!</p>

<p>This is a beer I&rsquo;ve brewed a lot before and I&rsquo;ve gone through a great deal of
experimentation before arriving at a flavor profile I really loved. I&rsquo;ve gone
through various yeast strains and hop varieties. I particularly love the
introduction of american citrusy hops with the french saison strain, so we&rsquo;ll
be using lots of that.</p>

<p>To play homage to the all-but-the-kitchen-sink tradition of farmhouse ales, I
added just a bit of flaked rye to this recipe. I&rsquo;ve always had some flaked
wheat in there too, yielding an awesome, white long lasting head.</p>

<p>It is still a very light grist, and based on the success of using acidulated
malt in <a href="/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/">a recent
brew</a>, I decided to add
some of that here as well.  Unfortunately that didn&rsquo;t turn out very well (read
more below!), so I will be reducing or removing that completely next time I
brew this beer.</p>

<p>The recipe is:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th> Boil Time </th>
<th> IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td> 60m       </td>
<td> 72    </td>
<td> 1.065 </td>
<td> 1.006 </td>
<td> 7.8 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Note that IBU is estimated, as First Worth Hopping IBU contribution is unknown.</p>

<p><em>Water:</em></p>

<p>Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name             </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Gypsum           </td>
<td> &frac34; tsp </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Calcium Chloride </td>
<td> 1 tsp   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phosphoric Acid  </td>
<td> 0.5ml   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                  </th>
<th> Amount                     </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Belgian Pilsen        </td>
<td> 12.5 lb                    </td>
<td> 90.1%       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Wheat          </td>
<td> 8 oz                       </td>
<td> 3.6%        </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Rye            </td>
<td> 8 oz                       </td>
<td> 3.6%        </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acidulated Malt       </td>
<td> 6 oz (use less! See below) </td>
<td> 2.7%        </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Variety     </th>
<th> Time          </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Form       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Sorachi Ace </td>
<td> FWH           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mt. Hood    </td>
<td> 60m           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mt. Hood    </td>
<td> 15m           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Citra       </td>
<td> 5m            </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz        </td>
<td> 5m            </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Citra       </td>
<td> Steep for 15m </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz        </td>
<td> Steep for 15m </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount   </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a> </td>
<td> 1 lb     </td>
<td> 10m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Yeast:</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                         </th>
<th> Lab     </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> WY3711 French Saison         </td>
<td> WYeast  </td>
<td> 77 - 83%    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>July 3, 2015</h4>

<p>I treaded RO water per the recipe, lowering strike water pH to 6.1. Strike
water was at 162F, and the mash ended up at 146F. I quickly heated up some
water and added it in to raise the temperature to 151F.</p>

<p>Initial reading of the mash pH was 4.9. The acidulated malt present in the
mash, along with the phosphoric acid used, the very little buffering capacity in
my RO water, and the calcium added with the salt treatments, lowered the pH way
too much. <strong>Next time reduce or remove acidulated malt from grist!</strong> To solve
this, I added NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (Baking soda) in half teaspoon increments
until the mash adjusted up to 5.2. I added a total of one teaspoon and the pH
was spot on. Crisis adverted!</p>

<p>I mashed for 90 minutes, and fly-sparged for 40 minutes. I collected 8 gallons
of wort as I expect a lot of loss to the whole hops and the long boiling time.
Fired up the kettle and 17 minutes later I got the hot break. At this
point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Had a nice rolling boil for 90 minutes, adding hops and other additions per the
recipe. Ended up with 6.5 gallons in the kettle.</p>

<p>Chilled and collected 5.5 gallons of wort in the fermenter, spot on.</p>

<p>Pitched the yeast starter that I had prepared the previous day, and set it to
ferment at room temperature, about 68F.</p>

<p>Measured OG was 1.065</p>

<h4>July 26, 2015</h4>

<p>Kegged beer and left it at room temperature.
FG was 1.006. ABV is 7.8%</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Daddy's Belgian Blonde Ale]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-21T11:47:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;m brewing something I haven&rsquo;t brewed before: A belgian blonde.</p>

<p>My objectives with this beer are:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>Very crisp and clear appearance, should look a like a pilsener with good head.</li>
<li>A bit of a malty and toasty aroma and flavor.</li>
<li>Balanced hop bitterness and a bit of spicy hop aroma.</li>
<li>High gravity and alcohol.</li>
<li>Subtle and complex, easy drinking and delicious.</li>
</ul>


<p>The majority of the grist is belgian pilsener, but I&rsquo;m adding a bit of aromatic
malt to give it that distinct maltness that plays well with the pilsener. It
also has a bit of flaked wheat to aid with head retention and a bit of a creamy
body. I&rsquo;m also adding 2 pounds of light beet sugar from
<a href="http://candisyrup.com">candisyrup.com</a> to contribute some caramelly richness
but also to aid attenuation and get even higher gravity.</p>

<p>For this brew, I&rsquo;m keeping it very classic as it comes to hop schedule. This is
not a hoppy beer, and the hops' contribution should be that of balance and a
bit of spicyness.</p>

<p>The glowing star for this beer is the yeast. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of success with
WLP510 for big belgian brews, and I think it&rsquo;ll fit well with this beer for its
dry, acidic finish and the mild spicy notes it produces.</p>

<p>I plan on letting this one &ldquo;lager&rdquo; in a keg for at least a month before
carbonating to aid with clarification and let the high alcohol fusel flavors
mellow out.</p>

<p>The recipe ended up as follows:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th> Boil Time </th>
<th> IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td> 90m       </td>
<td> 20    </td>
<td> 1.065 </td>
<td> 1.009 </td>
<td> 7.1 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Water</em></p>

<p>Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name             </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Calcium Chloride </td>
<td> 1 tsp   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gypsum           </td>
<td> &frac34; tsp </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phosphoric Acid  </td>
<td> 0.5ml   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                  </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Belgian Pilsen Malt   </td>
<td> 13lb   </td>
<td> 92%         </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aromatic Malt         </td>
<td> 10oz   </td>
<td> 4.4%        </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Wheat          </td>
<td> 8oz    </td>
<td> 3.5%        </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Hop schedule</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Variety   </th>
<th> Time   </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Form       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Hallertau </td>
<td> 60m    </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz      </td>
<td> 60m    </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hallertau </td>
<td> 2m     </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz      </td>
<td> 2m     </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole hops </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Other</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount   </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a> </td>
<td> 2 lb     </td>
<td> 10m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Yeast</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                       </th>
<th> Lab         </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> WLP510 Bastogne Ale Yeast  </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 74 - 80%    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.
Boil for 90 minutes to reduce chance of DMS.</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>June 21</h4>

<p>I Treated RO water per the recipe. This brought strike water pH down to 6.1.
Along with the salt additions, the mash pH was on target, at 5.4.  Didn&rsquo;t have
to treat mash pH at all, even for such a light-colored grist.  The approach of
using phosphoric acid in strike water rather than adding acidulated malt is one
that works well.</p>

<p>I mashed at 151F.</p>

<p>For sparge water, I added 0.5ml of phosphoric acid which brought it down to a
pH of 5.7. This is about the right amount of phosphoric acid to add the sparge
water without overshooting it!</p>

<p><a href="https://instagram.com/p/4NVgr1H2cu/?taken-by=flyinghopmachine">I collected 8 gallons of 1.055 wort</a>.</p>

<p>Fired up the kettle, it started boiling 12 minutes later, and got to the hot
break 4 minutes after that. At this point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Added kettle additions per the recipe.</p>

<p>Post-boil volume was 6.3 gallons. Chilled and transfered to fermenter where I
aerated for roughly 40 minutes.</p>

<p>Pitched two vials of WLP510 as I hadn&rsquo;t prepared a starter this time around.
Stored fermenter at room temperature where it will sit for ~2 weeks.</p>

<p>OG was 1.065</p>

<h4>July 12</h4>

<p>Kegged and took <a href="https://instagram.com/p/5DXyEgn2ck/">a gravity reading</a>. Ended
at 1.011. Leaving at room temp until there&rsquo;s space in my keezer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Drink with the flies IPA v2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T22:05:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently brewed an IPA using only New Zealand and Australian hop varieties. I
was shooting for a very light colored, clear, crisp, and fruity IPA to enjoy in
the summer. <a href="https://instagram.com/p/4F-drjn2Qs/?taken-by=flyinghopmachine">Here&rsquo;s a
photo</a>. I used a
very simple grain bill consisting of 50/50 domestic 2-row and pilsener malts,
and added a half pound of wheat to aid in head retention.</p>

<p>For hops, I used Waimea, Australian Summer and Nelson Saivan as follows:</p>

<!--more-->


<p>FWH: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin<br>
30m: 1 oz Waimea<br>
5m: 1oz Australian Summer, 1oz Waimea<br>
0m: 1oz Nelson Sauvin 1oz Australian Summer<br>
Dry hop for 3 days: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin</p>

<p>I was also experimenting with large First Wort Hopping (FWH) additions while
avoiding any bittering additions at all. I was trying to see how much bittering
I could get from FWH alone. It may have been the hops used, or the process
itself, but I didn&rsquo;t really get much bittering from FWH, so that might be a
good technique for extracting a small amount of bittering from hops and
avoiding harsh bitterness. It&rsquo;s hard to tell how much of the flavor and aroma
profile comes from FWH in this beer as it had many other later hop additions.</p>

<p>In any case, it&rsquo;s an easy enough technique that I&rsquo;ll be including in more of my
brews going forward.</p>

<h2>Beer issues</h2>

<p>The resulting beer was OK, but it had some issues that I will address in this
version. Of course some of these are subjective, the brew itself was solid and
people wo try it seem to like it.</p>

<h3>Color and mouth feel</h3>

<p>It didn&rsquo;t have enough of a malt backbone, and honestly it fell a bit flat and
uninteresting. The color was super pale and yellow, which I was going for, but
I think it could use a bit more color, too.</p>

<p>To address this, I&rsquo;m changing the grist by removing the pilsener malt, and
replacing it with more 2-row and some Vienna and Munich malts to layer some
complexity without adding any significant sweetness. I&rsquo;m also adding a bit
of dextrin to increase body.</p>

<h3>Hop aroma</h3>

<p>It could definitely use more hop aroma and bitterness. I&rsquo;m now adding a proper
bittering addition with CTZ, one of my go-to bittering hops for it&rsquo;s high alpha
acid content. I&rsquo;m also pushing more hops to the later additions to get more
flavor out of them, and throwing Galaxy into the mix to get even more of a
tropical and grapefruit aroma and flavor.</p>

<p>In general, I like the direction of this combination of hops though, and that
remains the focus of my &ldquo;Drink with the flies&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Yeast selection</h3>

<p>It could use a bit more ester production in fermentation, so I am switching
<a href="http://www.whitelabs.com/yeast/wlp001-california-ale-yeast">WLP001</a> with a bit
more flavorful but dry strain,
<a href="http://www.whitelabs.com/yeast/wlp007-dry-english-ale-yeast">WLP007</a>.</p>

<h3>Mash pH</h3>

<p>My mash pH on the last brew was at 5.8 and I corrected it by adding some
phosphoric acid right in the mash cooler. For this brew I&rsquo;ve changed the grist
by adding some Vienna and Munich malts, which are toasted malts that might add
some acidity in the mash, but not quite enough to get it to the 5.4 range. I&rsquo;m
keeping my salt additions as is, but also adding acidulated malt to help lower
the pH to 5.4.</p>

<p>The final recipe looks like this:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th> Boil Time </th>
<th> IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td> 60m       </td>
<td> 72    </td>
<td> 1.078 </td>
<td> 1.012 </td>
<td> 8.8 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Water</em></p>

<p>Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name             </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Gypsum           </td>
<td> 1.5 tsp </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Calcium Chloride </td>
<td> &frac14; tsp </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phosphoric Acid  </td>
<td> 0.5ml   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Add &frac12; tsp gypsum in boil.</p>

<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                  </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Rahr 2-row            </td>
<td> 12 lb  </td>
<td> 73.8 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vienna Malt           </td>
<td> 2 lb   </td>
<td> 12.3 %      </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Light Munich Malt     </td>
<td> 1 lb   </td>
<td> 6.2 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dextrin               </td>
<td> 8 oz   </td>
<td> 3.1 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wheat Malt            </td>
<td> 8 oz   </td>
<td> 3.1 %       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acidulated Malt       </td>
<td> 4 oz   </td>
<td> 1.5 %       </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Mash at 149F for 90 minutes.</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule:</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Variety           </th>
<th> Time                      </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Form       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Nelson Sauvin     </td>
<td> FWH                       </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Centennial        </td>
<td> 60m                       </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Australian Summer </td>
<td> 2m                        </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Waimea            </td>
<td> 2m                        </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Galaxy            </td>
<td> 2m                        </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Waimea            </td>
<td> Steep for 15m             </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Galaxy            </td>
<td> Steep for 15m             </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Waimea            </td>
<td> Dry hop 3 days            </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nelson Sauvin     </td>
<td> Dry hop 3 days            </td>
<td> 2oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Galaxy            </td>
<td> Dry hop 3 days (separate) </td>
<td> 2 oz   </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Yeast</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                         </th>
<th> Lab         </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> WLP007 Dry English Ale Yeast </td>
<td> White Labs  </td>
<td> 70 - 80%    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>June 20, 2015</h4>

<p>Mash ended up at 146F. Boiled a quart of water and adjusted up to 149.
Mash pH was on target, 5.4.</p>

<p>Sparge water (RO) pH was of 8.0. I added 3ml of phosphoric acid to bring it
down. It was way too much, brought it down to 3.6, so I had to troubleshoot. I
added 2g of more RO water, but the buffering capacity of this water is so low,
it only brought it up to 4.1. I then replaced 1g of this water with tap water,
which has huge alkalinity in my area, and that brought it up to 5.4. I added a
half of a campdem tablet to not screw with cholrine which has given me
<a href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/">problems</a>
before. Final Sparge water pH was 5.3.</p>

<p>I sparged for 45m and collected 7.6g of wort. Waited for hot break which took
about 10m, and started the 60m hop addition.</p>

<p>At 15 minutes left of the boil, added a whirfloc tablet, something I do with
all my brews.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t have enough hop bags, was missing one for the steap additions. I
decided to remove the CTZ bag, clean it up, and use that for the steap
addition. I didn&rsquo;t want to risk having too much trub in the kettle, but this
worked well. I removed the CTZ bag 1 minute before the boil was done.</p>

<p>Chilled down to 68 F with a plate chiller. Aerated wort for 40m, pitched my
yeast starter, and attached a blow-off tube right away. I expect this to be an
aggressive fermentation because of gravity and yeast choice.</p>

<p>OG: 1.078. This is Double IPA territory :)</p>

<h4>July 3, 2015</h4>

<p>Kegged beer. Gravity reading was 1.020, but it is still
fermenting. Also added dry hops of 1oz Waimea and 2 oz Nelson Saivon.</p>

<h4>July 6, 2015</h4>

<p>Removed Waimea and Nelson Saivon dry hop bags</p>

<h4>July 9, 2015</h4>

<p>Dry hopped with 2oz Galaxy</p>

<h4>July 13, 2015</h4>

<p>Removed 2oz Galaxy dry hops.
Smells heavily of passionfruit, might as well call it passion IPA! :)
It appears to continue to ferment as it is still generating CO<sub>2</sub>, so
leaving it in keg at room temperature until activity stops.</p>

<h4>July 25, 2015</h4>

<p>FG: 1.012 (resulting in an 8.8% ABV DIPA)
Set it in keezer and began carbonation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
