<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: brewday | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/brewday/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-04T19:02:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Independence Saison]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T20:36:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I brewed a variation on a recipe that I&rsquo;ve worked on for some time. This
beer is being brewed for a special professional event. I&rsquo;ll be given the chance
to talk about the brewing process, and given the audience is engineers and
bio-medical scientists I might dive into water chemistry and focus on that.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I was asked to bring what I consider to be &ldquo;my best brew.&rdquo; This is of course a
terrible question to ask a brewer, just like a dad doesn&rsquo;t have a favorite
child. Right, right? So instead I thought about who the audience is, what the
environment is like, and what I thought they&rsquo;d like the most. There will be
other homebrewers and there will be a prize for best beer, so let&rsquo;s aim for
that! In this case, I think I&rsquo;ll be pouring beer to engineers who are open to
some experimentation but aren&rsquo;t really familiar with the breadth of flavors that
exist in beer, so I wanted to step a bit outside their comfort area while still
bringing something approachable and very drinkable for many palettes. I had to
stay away from harsh or aggressive flavors, but want it to be exotic enough to
leave an impression. Things like barley wine, double/tripple IPAs, Imperial
stouts, might be a bit too aggressive for this purpose. On the other hand Pale
Ales, Pilseners, or Kölsh might be too safe. I decided to go with a saison that
has enough of an edge to be interesting, but might be familiar in other ways
such as color and hop profile. We&rsquo;ll see how this goes!</p>

<p>This is a beer I&rsquo;ve brewed a lot before and I&rsquo;ve gone through a great deal of
experimentation before arriving at a flavor profile I really loved. I&rsquo;ve gone
through various yeast strains and hop varieties. I particularly love the
introduction of american citrusy hops with the french saison strain, so we&rsquo;ll
be using lots of that.</p>

<p>To play homage to the all-but-the-kitchen-sink tradition of farmhouse ales, I
added just a bit of flaked rye to this recipe. I&rsquo;ve always had some flaked
wheat in there too, yielding an awesome, white long lasting head.</p>

<p>It is still a very light grist, and based on the success of using acidulated
malt in <a href="/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/">a recent
brew</a>, I decided to add
some of that here as well.  Unfortunately that didn&rsquo;t turn out very well (read
more below!), so I will be reducing or removing that completely next time I
brew this beer.</p>

<p>The recipe is:</p>

<p><em>Water:</em></p>

<p>Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1tsp Calcium Chloride</li>
<li>&frac34; tsp Gypsum</li>
<li>0.5ml phosphoric acid</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Grain bill:</em></p>

<p>12.5 lb Belgian Pilsener (Castle)<br>
8 oz Flakes Wheat<br>
8 oz Flakes Rye<br>
8 oz Flakes Rye<br>
6 oz Acidulated Malt (Use less! See below)</p>

<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule:</em></p>

<p>FWH: Sorachi Ace<br>
60m: Mt. Hood<br>
15m: Mt. Hood<br>
5m: 1oz Citra &amp; 1oz Saaz<br>
Steep 15m: 1oz Citra &amp; 1oz Saaz<br></p>

<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<p>15m: Whirfloc tablet<br>
15m: 1 lb <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a></p>

<p><em>Yeast:</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.wyeastlab.com/rw_yeaststrain_detail.cfm?ID=199">WY3711 French Saison</a>.</p>

<p><em>Dry hop:</em></p>

<p>2 oz of Amarillo for 5 days in secondary/keg.</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<p>I treaded RO water per the recipe, lowering strike water pH to 6.1. Strike
water was at 162F, and the mash ended up at 146F. I quickly heated up some
water and added it in to raise the temperature to 151F.</p>

<p>Initial reading of the mash pH was 4.9. The acidulated malt present in the
mash, along with the phosphoric acid used, the very little buffering capacity in
my RO water, and the calcium added with the salt treatments, lowered the pH way
too much. <strong>Next time reduce or remove acidulated malt from grist!</strong> To solve
this, I added NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (Baking soda) in half teaspoon increments
until the mash adjusted up to 5.2. I added a total of one teaspoon and the pH
was spot on. Crisis adverted!</p>

<p>I mashed for 90 minutes, and fly-sparged for 40 minutes. I collected 8 gallons
of wort as I expect a lot of loss to the whole hops and the long boiling time.
Fired up the kettle and 17 minutes later I got the hot break. At this
point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Had a nice rolling boil for 90 minutes, adding hops and other additions per the
recipe. Ended up with 6.5 gallons in the kettle.</p>

<p>Chilled and collected 5.5 gallons of wort in the fermenter, spot on.</p>

<p>Pitched the yeast starter that I had prepared the previous day, and set it to
ferment at room temperature, about 68F.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Daddy's Belgian Blonde Ale]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-21T11:47:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;m brewing something I haven&rsquo;t brewed before: A belgian blonde.</p>

<p>My objectives with this beer are:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>Very crisp and clear appearance, should look a like a pilsener with good head.</li>
<li>A bit of a malty and toasty aroma and flavor.</li>
<li>Balanced hop bitterness and a bit of spicy hop aroma.</li>
<li>High gravity and alcohol.</li>
<li>Subtle and complex, easy drinking and delicious.</li>
</ul>


<p>The majority of the grist is belgian pilsener, but I&rsquo;m adding a bit of aromatic
malt to give it that distinct maltness that plays well with the pilsener. It
also has a bit of flaked wheat to aid with head retention and a bit of a creamy
body. I&rsquo;m also adding 2 pounds of light beet sugar from
<a href="http://candisyrup.com">candisyrup.com</a> to contribute some caramelly richness
but also to aid attenuation and get even higher gravity.</p>

<p>For this brew, I&rsquo;m keeping it very classic as it comes to hop schedule. This is
not a hoppy beer, and the hops' contribution should be that of balance and a
bit of spicyness.</p>

<p>The glowing star for this beer is the yeast. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of success with
WLP510 for big belgian brews, and I think it&rsquo;ll fit well with this beer for its
dry, acidic finish and the mild spicy notes it produces.</p>

<p>I plan on letting this one &ldquo;lager&rdquo; in a keg for at least a month before
carbonating to aid with clarification and let the high alcohol fusel flavors
mellow out.</p>

<p>The recipe ended up as follows:</p>

<p><em>Water</em>:
Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1tsp Calcium Chloride</li>
<li>&frac34; tsp Gypsum</li>
<li>0.5ml phosphoric acid</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Grain bill:</em></p>

<p>13 lb Belgian Pilsener Malt<br>
10 oz Aromatic Malt<br>
8 oz Flaked Wheat</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule:</em></p>

<p>60m: 1 oz Hallertau &amp; 1oz Saaz<br>
2m: 5 0z Hallertau &amp; 1 oz Saaz</p>

<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<p>Whirfloc tablet at 15 minutes left of the boil<br>
2 lb <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a></p>

<p>WLP510 - Bastogne Ale Yeast</p>

<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.
Boil for 90 minutes to reduce chance of DMS.</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<p>I Treated RO water per the recipe. This brought strike water pH down to 6.1.
Along with the salt additions, the mash pH was on target, at 5.4.  Didn&rsquo;t have
to treat mash pH at all, even for such a light-colored grist.  The approach of
using phosphoric acid in strike water rather than adding acidulated malt is one
that works well.</p>

<p>I mashed at 151F.</p>

<p>For sparge water, I added 0.5ml of phosphoric acid which brought it down to a
pH of 5.7. This is about the right amount of phosphoric acid to add the sparge
water without overshooting it!</p>

<p><a href="https://instagram.com/p/4NVgr1H2cu/?taken-by=flyinghopmachine">I collected 8 gallons of 1.055 wort</a>.</p>

<p>Fired up the kettle, it started boiling 12 minutes later, and got to the hot
break 4 minutes after that. At this point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Added kettle additions per the recipe.</p>

<p>Post-boil volume was 6.3 gallons. Chilled and transfered to fermenter where I
aerated for roughly 40 minutes.</p>

<p>Pitched two vials of WLP510 as I hadn&rsquo;t prepared a starter this time around.
Stored fermenter at room temperature where it will sit for ~2 weeks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Drink with the flies IPA v2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T22:05:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently brewed an IPA using only New Zealand and Australian hop varieties. I
was shooting for a very light colored, clear, crisp, and fruity IPA to enjoy in
the summer. <a href="https://instagram.com/p/4F-drjn2Qs/?taken-by=flyinghopmachine">Here&rsquo;s a
photo</a>. I used a
very simple grain bill consisting of 50/50 domestic 2-row and pilsener malts,
and added a half pound of wheat to aid in head retention.</p>

<p>For hops, I used Waimea, Australian Summer and Nelson Saivan as follows:</p>

<!--more-->


<p>FWH: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin<br>
30m: 1 oz Waimea<br>
5m: 1oz Australian Summer, 1oz Waimea<br>
0m: 1oz Nelson Sauvin 1oz Australian Summer<br>
Dry hop for 3 days: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin</p>

<p>I was also experimenting with large First Wort Hopping (FWH) additions while
avoiding any bittering additions at all. I was trying to see how much bittering
I could get from FWH alone. It may have been the hops used, or the process
itself, but I didn&rsquo;t really get much bittering from FWH, so that might be a
good technique for extracting a small amount of bittering from hops and
avoiding harsh bitterness. It&rsquo;s hard to tell how much of the flavor and aroma
profile comes from FWH in this beer as it had many other later hop additions.</p>

<p>In any case, it&rsquo;s an easy enough technique that I&rsquo;ll be including in more of my
brews going forward.</p>

<h2>Beer issues</h2>

<p>The resulting beer was OK, but it had some issues that I will address in this
version. Of course some of these are subjective, the brew itself was solid and
people wo try it seem to like it.</p>

<h3>Color and mouth feel</h3>

<p>It didn&rsquo;t have enough of a malt backbone, and honestly it fell a bit flat and
uninteresting. The color was super pale and yellow, which I was going for, but
I think it could use a bit more color, too.</p>

<p>To address this, I&rsquo;m changing the grist by removing the pilsener malt, and
replacing it with more 2-row and some Vienna and Munich malts to layer some
complexity without adding any significant sweetness. I&rsquo;m also adding a bit
of dextrin to increase body.</p>

<h3>Hop aroma</h3>

<p>It could definitely use more hop aroma and bitterness. I&rsquo;m now adding a proper
bittering addition with CTZ, one of my go-to bittering hops for it&rsquo;s high alpha
acid content. I&rsquo;m also pushing more hops to the later additions to get more
flavor out of them, and throwing Galaxy into the mix to get even more of a
tropical and grapefruit aroma and flavor.</p>

<p>In general, I like the direction of this combination of hops though, and that
remains the focus of my &ldquo;Drink with the flies&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Yeast selection</h3>

<p>It could use a bit more ester production in fermentation, so I am switching
<a href="http://www.whitelabs.com/yeast/wlp001-california-ale-yeast">WLP001</a> with a bit
more flavorful but dry strain,
<a href="http://www.whitelabs.com/yeast/wlp007-dry-english-ale-yeast">WLP007</a>.</p>

<h3>Mash pH</h3>

<p>My mash pH on the last brew was at 5.8 and I corrected it by adding some
phosphoric acid right in the mash cooler. For this brew I&rsquo;ve changed the grist
by adding some Vienna and Munich malts, which are toasted malts that might add
some acidity in the mash, but not quite enough to get it to the 5.4 range. I&rsquo;m
keeping my salt additions as is, but also adding acidulated malt to help lower
the pH to 5.4.</p>

<p>The final recipe looks like this:</p>

<p><em>Water treatments:</em></p>

<p>RO treated with 1.5tsp gypsum and &frac14; tsp calcium chloride in
strike water. Add &frac12; tsp gypsum in boil.<br>
<br>Lower sparge water to a pH of 5.4 with phosphoric acid.</p>

<p><em>Grain bill:</em></p>

<p>12 lb Rahr 2-row<br>
2 lb Vienna Malt<br>
1 lb Ligh Munich Malt<br>
8oz Dextrin<br>
8oz Wheat Malt<br>
4oz Acidulated Malt</p>

<p>Mash at 149F for 90 minutes.</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule:</em></p>

<p>FWH: 1oz Nelson Sauvin<br>
60m: 1z CTZ<br>
5m: 10z Nelson Sauvin &amp; 1oz Australian Summer<br>
2m: 1oz Australian Summer, 1oz Waimea &amp; 1oz Galaxy<br>
Steep for 20m: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Galaxy<br></p>

<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<p>Whirfloc tablet at 15 minutes left of the boil</p>

<p>Dry hop for 3 days:<br>
1 oz Waimea &amp; 2 oz Galaxy</p>

<p>WLP007 - Dry English Ale Yeast</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<p>Mash ended up at 146F. Boiled a quart of water and adjusted up to 149.
Mash pH was on target, 5.4.</p>

<p>Sparge water (RO) pH was of 8.0. I added 3ml of phosphoric acid to bring it
down. It was way too much, brought it down to 3.6, so I had to troubleshoot. I
added 2g of more RO water, but the buffering capacity of this water is so low,
it only brought it up to 4.1. I then replaced 1g of this water with tap water,
which has huge alkalinity in my area, and that brought it up to 5.4. I added a
half of a campdem tablet to not screw with cholrine which has given me
<a href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/">problems</a>
before. Final Sparge water pH was 5.3.</p>

<p>I sparged for 45m and collected 7.6g of wort. Waited for hot break which took
about 10m, and started the 60m hop addition.</p>

<p>At 15 minutes left of the boil, added a whirfloc tablet, something I do with
all my brews.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t have enough hop bags, was missing one for the steap additions. I
decided to remove the CTZ bag, clean it up, and use that for the steap
addition. I didn&rsquo;t want to risk having too much trub in the kettle, but this
worked well. I removed the CTZ bag 1 minute before the boil was done.</p>

<p>Chilled down to 68 F with a plate chiller. Aerated wort for 40m, pitched my yeast starter, and attached a blow-off tube right away. I expect this to be an aggressive fermentation because of gravity and yeast choice.</p>

<p>OG: 1.078. This is Double IPA territory :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
