<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: belgian | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/belgian/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-04T11:15:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Daddy's Belgian Blonde Ale]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-21T11:47:05-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/21/brew-day-daddys-belgian-blonde-ale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;m brewing something I haven&rsquo;t brewed before: A belgian blonde.</p>

<p>My objectives with this beer are:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>Very crisp and clear appearance, should look a like a pilsener with good head.</li>
<li>A bit of a malty and toasty aroma and flavor.</li>
<li>Balanced hop bitterness and a bit of spicy hop aroma.</li>
<li>High gravity and alcohol.</li>
<li>Subtle and complex, easy drinking and delicious.</li>
</ul>


<p>The majority of the grist is belgian pilsener, but I&rsquo;m adding a bit of aromatic
malt to give it that distinct maltness that plays well with the pilsener. It
also has a bit of flaked wheat to aid with head retention and a bit of a creamy
body. I&rsquo;m also adding 2 pounds of light beet sugar from
<a href="http://candisyrup.com">candisyrup.com</a> to contribute some caramelly richness
but also to aid attenuation and get even higher gravity.</p>

<p>For this brew, I&rsquo;m keeping it very classic as it comes to hop schedule. This is
not a hoppy beer, and the hops' contribution should be that of balance and a
bit of spicyness.</p>

<p>The glowing star for this beer is the yeast. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of success with
WLP510 for big belgian brews, and I think it&rsquo;ll fit well with this beer for its
dry, acidic finish and the mild spicy notes it produces.</p>

<p>I plan on letting this one &ldquo;lager&rdquo; in a keg for at least a month before
carbonating to aid with clarification and let the high alcohol fusel flavors
mellow out.</p>

<p>The recipe ended up as follows:</p>

<p><em>Water</em>:
Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<ul>
<li>1tsp Calcium Chloride</li>
<li>&frac34; tsp Gypsum</li>
<li>0.5ml phosphoric acid</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Grain bill:</em></p>

<p>13 lb Belgian Pilsener Malt<br>
10 oz Aromatic Malt<br>
8 oz Flaked Wheat</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule:</em></p>

<p>60m: 1 oz Hallertau &amp; 1oz Saaz<br>
2m: 5 0z Hallertau &amp; 1 oz Saaz</p>

<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<p>Whirfloc tablet at 15 minutes left of the boil<br>
2 lb <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a></p>

<p>WLP510 - Bastogne Ale Yeast</p>

<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.
Boil for 90 minutes to reduce chance of DMS.</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<p>I Treated RO water per the recipe. This brought strike water pH down to 6.1.
Along with the salt additions, the mash pH was on target, at 5.4.  Didn&rsquo;t have
to treat mash pH at all, even for such a light-colored grist.  The approach of
using phosphoric acid in strike water rather than adding acidulated malt is one
that works well.</p>

<p>I mashed at 151F.</p>

<p>For sparge water, I added 0.5ml of phosphoric acid which brought it down to a
pH of 5.7. This is about the right amount of phosphoric acid to add the sparge
water without overshooting it!</p>

<p><a href="https://instagram.com/p/4NVgr1H2cu/?taken-by=flyinghopmachine">I collected 8 gallons of 1.055 wort</a>.</p>

<p>Fired up the kettle, it started boiling 12 minutes later, and got to the hot
break 4 minutes after that. At this point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Added kettle additions per the recipe.</p>

<p>Post-boil volume was 6.3 gallons. Chilled and transfered to fermenter where I
aerated for roughly 40 minutes.</p>

<p>Pitched two vials of WLP510 as I hadn&rsquo;t prepared a starter this time around.
Stored fermenter at room temperature where it will sit for ~2 weeks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
