<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: saison | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/saison/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-29T22:53:21-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew day: Independence Saison]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T20:36:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/07/03/brew-day-independence-saison</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I brewed a variation on a recipe that I&rsquo;ve worked on for some time. This
beer is being brewed for a special professional event. I&rsquo;ll be given the chance
to talk about the brewing process, and given the audience is engineers and
bio-medical scientists I might dive into water chemistry and focus on that.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I was asked to bring what I consider to be &ldquo;my best brew.&rdquo; This is of course a
terrible question to ask a brewer, just like a dad doesn&rsquo;t have a favorite
child. Right, right? So instead I thought about who the audience is, what the
environment is like, and what I thought they&rsquo;d like the most. There will be
other homebrewers and there will be a prize for best beer, so let&rsquo;s aim for
that! In this case, I think I&rsquo;ll be pouring beer to engineers who are open to
some experimentation but aren&rsquo;t really familiar with the breadth of flavors that
exist in beer, so I wanted to step a bit outside their comfort area while still
bringing something approachable and very drinkable for many palettes. I had to
stay away from harsh or aggressive flavors, but want it to be exotic enough to
leave an impression. Things like barley wine, double/tripple IPAs, Imperial
stouts, might be a bit too aggressive for this purpose. On the other hand Pale
Ales, Pilseners, or Kölsh might be too safe. I decided to go with a saison that
has enough of an edge to be interesting, but might be familiar in other ways
such as color and hop profile. We&rsquo;ll see how this goes!</p>

<p>This is a beer I&rsquo;ve brewed a lot before and I&rsquo;ve gone through a great deal of
experimentation before arriving at a flavor profile I really loved. I&rsquo;ve gone
through various yeast strains and hop varieties. I particularly love the
introduction of american citrusy hops with the french saison strain, so we&rsquo;ll
be using lots of that.</p>

<p>To play homage to the all-but-the-kitchen-sink tradition of farmhouse ales, I
added just a bit of flaked rye to this recipe. I&rsquo;ve always had some flaked
wheat in there too, yielding an awesome, white long lasting head.</p>

<p>It is still a very light grist, and based on the success of using acidulated
malt in <a href="/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/">a recent
brew</a>, I decided to add
some of that here as well.  Unfortunately that didn&rsquo;t turn out very well (read
more below!), so I will be reducing or removing that completely next time I
brew this beer.</p>

<p>The recipe is:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Batch Size </th>
<th> Boil Time </th>
<th> IBU   </th>
<th> OG    </th>
<th> FG    </th>
<th> ABV </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 6g         </td>
<td> 60m       </td>
<td> 72    </td>
<td> 1.065 </td>
<td> 1.006 </td>
<td> 7.8 </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Note that IBU is estimated, as First Worth Hopping IBU contribution is unknown.</p>

<p><em>Water:</em></p>

<p>Start with RO water. Treat strike water with:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name             </th>
<th> Amount  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Gypsum           </td>
<td> &frac34; tsp </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Calcium Chloride </td>
<td> 1 tsp   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Phosphoric Acid  </td>
<td> 0.5ml   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Fermentables</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                  </th>
<th> Amount                     </th>
<th> Percent     </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Belgian Pilsen        </td>
<td> 12.5 lb                    </td>
<td> 90.1%       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Wheat          </td>
<td> 8 oz                       </td>
<td> 3.6%        </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Flaked Rye            </td>
<td> 8 oz                       </td>
<td> 3.6%        </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acidulated Malt       </td>
<td> 6 oz (use less! See below) </td>
<td> 2.7%        </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Mash at 151F for 90 minutes.</p>

<p><em>Hop schedule</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Variety     </th>
<th> Time          </th>
<th> Amount </th>
<th> Form       </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Sorachi Ace </td>
<td> FWH           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Palletes   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mt. Hood    </td>
<td> 60m           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mt. Hood    </td>
<td> 15m           </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Citra       </td>
<td> 5m            </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz        </td>
<td> 5m            </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Citra       </td>
<td> Steep for 15m </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Saaz        </td>
<td> Steep for 15m </td>
<td> 1oz    </td>
<td> Whole Hops </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Other:</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                                             </th>
<th> Amount   </th>
<th> Use              </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Whirlfloc                                        </td>
<td> 1 tablet </td>
<td> 15m left in boil </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <a href="http://www.candisyrup.com/">Golden Candi Syrup</a> </td>
<td> 1 lb     </td>
<td> 10m left in boil </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p><em>Yeast:</em></p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name                         </th>
<th> Lab     </th>
<th> Attenuation </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> WY3711 French Saison         </td>
<td> WYeast  </td>
<td> 77 - 83%    </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<h4>July 3, 2015</h4>

<p>I treaded RO water per the recipe, lowering strike water pH to 6.1. Strike
water was at 162F, and the mash ended up at 146F. I quickly heated up some
water and added it in to raise the temperature to 151F.</p>

<p>Initial reading of the mash pH was 4.9. The acidulated malt present in the
mash, along with the phosphoric acid used, the very little buffering capacity in
my RO water, and the calcium added with the salt treatments, lowered the pH way
too much. <strong>Next time reduce or remove acidulated malt from grist!</strong> To solve
this, I added NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (Baking soda) in half teaspoon increments
until the mash adjusted up to 5.2. I added a total of one teaspoon and the pH
was spot on. Crisis adverted!</p>

<p>I mashed for 90 minutes, and fly-sparged for 40 minutes. I collected 8 gallons
of wort as I expect a lot of loss to the whole hops and the long boiling time.
Fired up the kettle and 17 minutes later I got the hot break. At this
point I started the 90 minute boil.</p>

<p>Had a nice rolling boil for 90 minutes, adding hops and other additions per the
recipe. Ended up with 6.5 gallons in the kettle.</p>

<p>Chilled and collected 5.5 gallons of wort in the fermenter, spot on.</p>

<p>Pitched the yeast starter that I had prepared the previous day, and set it to
ferment at room temperature, about 68F.</p>

<p>Measured OG was 1.065</p>

<h4>July 26, 2015</h4>

<p>Kegged beer and left it at room temperature.
FG was 1.006. ABV is 7.8%</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
