<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ipa | Flying Hop Machine]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/categories/ipa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-19T23:05:32-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harold Giménez]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harold.gimenez+flyinghopmachine@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brew Day: Drink with the flies IPA v2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T22:05:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.flyinghopmachine.com/blog/2015/06/20/brew-day-drink-with-the-flies-ipa-v2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently brewed an IPA using only New Zealand and Australian hop varieties. I
was shooting for a very light colored, clear, crisp, and fruity IPA to enjoy in
the summer. I used a very simple grain bill consisting of 50/50 domestic 2-row
and pilsener malts, and added a half pound of wheat to aid in head retention.</p>

<p>For hops, I used Waimea, Australian Summer and Nelson Saivan as follows:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>FWH: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin</li>
<li>30m: 1 oz Waimea</li>
<li>5m: 1oz Australian Summer, 1oz Waimea</li>
<li>0m: 1oz Nelson Sauvin 1oz Australian Summer</li>
<li>Dry hop for 3 days: 1oz Waimea, 1oz Nelson Sauvin</li>
</ul>


<p>I was also experimenting with large First Wort Hopping (FWH) additions while
avoiding any bittering additions at all. I was trying to see how much bittering
I could get from FWH alone. It may have been the hops used, or the process
itself, but I didn&rsquo;t really get much bittering from FWH, so that might be a
good technique for extracting a small amount of bittering from hops. It&rsquo;s hard
to tell how much of the flavor and aroma profile comes from FWH in this beer as
it had many other later hop additions.</p>

<p>In any case, it&rsquo;s an easy enough technique that I&rsquo;ll be including in more of my
brews going forward.</p>

<h2>Beer issues</h2>

<p>The resulting beer was OK, but it had some issues that I will address in this
version:</p>

<h3>Color and mouth feel</h3>

<p>It didn&rsquo;t have enough of a malt backbone, and honestly it fell a bit flat and
uninteresting. The color was super pale and yellow, which I was going for, but
I think it could use a bit more color.</p>

<p>To address this, I&rsquo;m changing the grist by replacing some of the 2-row malt
with some Vienna and Munich malts to layer some complexity without adding any
significant sweetness, and adding I&rsquo;m also adding a bit of dextrin to increase
body.</p>

<h3>Hop aroma</h3>

<p>It could definitely use more hop aroma and bitterness. I&rsquo;m now adding a proper
bittering addition with Centennial, one of my go-to bittering hops for it&rsquo;s
high alpha acid content and low cost. I&rsquo;m also pushing more hops to the later
additions to get more flavor out of them, and throwing Galaxy into the mix
to get even more of a tropical and grapefruit aroma and flavor.</p>

<h3>Yeast selection</h3>

<p>It could use a bit more ester production in fermentation, so I am switching
WLP001 with a bit more flavorful but dry strain, WLP007.</p>

<h3>Mash pH</h3>

<p>My mash pH on the last brew was at 5.8 and I corrected it by adding some
phosphoric acid right in the mash cooler. While I have changed the grist, it&rsquo;s
still fairly, so this time around I&rsquo;m increasing the calcium content in the
mash to help it reach a level closer to 5.3. Last time I used 1.5tsp gypsum and
1/4tsp calcium chloride in my strike water. I&rsquo;ll increase that to 2tsp of
gypsum and a 1/2tsp of calcium chloride this time around.</p>

<p>The final recipe looks like this:</p>

<p>5 lb American 2-row<br>
7 lb American pilsener<br>
2 lb Vienna<br>
8 oz Munich<br>
12oz Dextrin<br>
8oz Wheat Malt</p>

<p>FWH: 1oz Nelson Sauvin<br>
60m: 1z Centennial<br>
15m: 1 oz Waimea<br>
5m: 1oz Australian Summer, 1oz Galaxy<br>
0m: 1oz Nelson Sauvin, 1oz Waimea</p>

<p>WLP007 - Dry English Ale Yeast</p>

<p>Dry hop for 3 days:<br>
1 oz Waimea, 1 oz Galaxy</p>

<h2>Brew notes</h2>

<p>(Coming soon&hellip;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
